Hi, I'm Tiara Vaian. KJZZ's audio service is supported by 1AZ Credit Union.
1AZ offers tools to help build personal savings, including traditional savings accounts and
share certificates. Learn more at 1AZCU.com.
This morning we're hearing at least 700 people are killed on the Israeli side with
more than 400 Palestinians dead in Gaza. We hear from a woman in Gaza.
The last couple of days were harrowing and the airstrikes were very frequent and huge.
Gaza is a very highly dense populated area with each and every missile very impactful
and damaging.
In Israel, rescuers say they found 260 bodies at the site of a music festival,
the first site attacked by Hamas.
We'll bring you the story of one family that is looking for their loved ones that
has been taken hostage by the Hamas militants.
And in other news, we'll go to Afghanistan, where an earthquake has killed more than
2,000 people. Rescue efforts are continuing. But first, we're getting a bulletin of
World News.
This is Danielle Yavavetska with the BBC News. Hello.
The Israeli military says its fighter jets, helicopters and artillery have struck over
500 targets overnight in the Gaza Strip. Operations are continuing against Palestinian
Hamas militants in several locations inside Israel, two days after they carried out
their devastating mass assault. More than 700 Israelis have been killed.
John Donison is in Jerusalem.
The Israeli military says it has continued to target Hamas infrastructure with airstrikes
overnight. The United Nations says more than 120,000 Gazans have now been displaced,
with many seeking shelter in UN schools. But most believe this is just the beginning.
Israel is massing its forces around Gaza and says it has called up around 100,000
army reservists. Palestinians are bracing themselves for a possible ground invasion,
with Israel saying its aim is to rescue hostages and remove Hamas from power in
Gaza.
Health officials in Gaza say more than 400 Palestinians have been killed so far
by Israeli airstrikes. Over 2,000 people have been injured. They said power cuts were
widespread and were posing a major challenge for medical workers. Hamas said it had fired
a new barrage of missiles into Israel. Three US air carriers, as well as Air
France, Lufthansa and Emirates, have suspended flights to Tel Aviv.
The United States says it is sending immediate extra munitions to Israel. The
Pentagon also announced it was deploying naval vessels, including an aircraft carrier,
to the eastern Mediterranean. More from Barbara Platasha in Washington.
The large deployment underscores American concerns that the conflict between Israel
and Hamas could draw in other parts of the region. They are sending an aircraft
carrier with a deck of warplanes, accompanied by cruisers and destroyers. Also extra
military assistance, such as munitions.
In particular, they want to prevent Lebanon's powerful Hezbollah movement from joining
the fight. It is backed by Iran, which also funds and arms Hamas. There are reports
that Iran helped organize the unprecedented attack, although the Secretary of State
Antony Blinken said the US hasn't seen evidence to confirm that.
The UN Security Council has held an emergency closed-door session to
discuss the crisis. The UN Middle East envoy called on countries to exert
diplomatic efforts to restore calm. More from Nedda Taufik in New York.
Council members did not attempt to reach agreement on a statement. Not all,
but many condemned Hamas. The UAE's ambassador to the UN, Lanin Acebe, told
reporters there was real concern that tensions in the region could become
inflamed. Before the meeting, Israel's ambassador to the UN, Gilad Erdan,
showed graphic pictures of Israeli civilians being taken captive by Hamas.
The Palestinian UN ambassador, Riyad Mansour, told reporters he'd
requested an emergency meeting of Arab League states in Cairo.
BBC World News.
An independent inquiry in the UK will begin hearings today into
allegations that British special forces killed dozens of unarmed
civilians, including children in Afghanistan. The inquiry was set up by
the British government after legal action was brought by two Afghan
families. The US Senate Majority Leader Chuck Schumer, who's leading a
bipartisan delegation to China, has met the Foreign Minister Wang Yi.
Mr Schumer is the latest high-level American official to visit as
Washington seeks to ease tensions with Beijing. Regional elections in two
of Germany's largest and wealthiest states, Bavaria and Hesse, have
dealt a blow to the parties that form the centre-left federal
government. Provisional results show losses for the Social Democrats,
the Greens and the liberal Free Democrats. The Christian Democrats
again emerge as the largest party. The president of Ecuador has
extended the state of emergency by 30 days. It's been in place since
the assassination in August of the anti-corruption presidential
candidate Fernando Villavicencio. The extension comes just days
after seven Colombians arrested over the killing were found dead
in prison. A hoard of coins believed to have belonged to a
Highland clan chief, who was murdered more than 300 years ago,
has been found in Scotland. Alexandra McKenzie reports.
The archaeology team from Glasgow University said this was the
first major excavation in Glencoe. The dig focused on scattered
rocks believed to have been the MacDonald clan chief's
summer house. More than 300 years after he died in the
Glencoe massacre, an archaeology student taking part in her
first ever dig found the hoard. The University of Glasgow said
the discovery contained 36 silver and bronze coins. A number of
other artifacts were also discovered at the site, including
a musket and fouling shot, pottery from across Europe and a
powder major. BBC News.
Thank you for that bulletin of news. Hello, your Newsday
from the BBC World Service with Victoria Wohonda and Rob
Young. Coming up this half hour, we're going to continue
to focus on the conflict between Israel and Gaza with
voices from both sides and we'll get all your sports and
business headlines too.
We are starting with the latest development in Israel and
Gaza as the numbers of those killed on both sides goes up
by the hour. The Israeli military says that at least 700
people have died in the attacks overall, with more than
2000 injured. The rescuers say that they found 260 bodies
at the site of a music festival attacked by Hamas
militants in the unprecedented assault on Saturday
morning. The wake of the attack took place on Saturday
The wave of attacks launched by the Hamas militant group
is being described as the biggest escalation between
the two sides for decades. In retaliation, Israel
launched airstrikes that have killed at least 400
people in the Gaza Strip with more than 2000 wounded,
according to the latest update from the Palestinian
officials. Video images show many buildings being
blown up in large-scale destruction. Shops are
closed. The streets are empty. The city is said to
be like a ghost town. According to the United Nations,
123,000 Palestinians have now been displaced in Gaza
because of the airstrikes. And many Palestinians say
they are now living in fear of their lives. In the
last hour, we got this voice note from a resident
in Gaza. The last couple of days were harrowing
and the airstrikes were very frequent and huge. Gaza
is a very highly dense populated area with very
limited geographical area, like with over 2 million
people living in 360 km2, which make it each
and every missile dropped very impactful and damaging.
The offensive launched from Gaza can only be
understood in the context of the Israeli ongoing
decades-long military occupation and settler
colonization of Palestinian land and the
composition of a system of oppression that meets
the legal definition of apartheid. Meanwhile,
Israeli also has maintained a brutal placate
on Gaza for 17 years against Palestinians
refusing its population access to basic supplies
and material needs to survive and trapping them
in amounts to an open air prison with restrictions
on right to movement, right to help and many
other associated basic rights. Yet we were told
as civilians to leave. I mean, leave and go
where? No crossings are open, neither the
sea that is also have restriction to some point.
If you trespass, you can be shot. For the
past few days, hundreds of Palestinians were
killed, including women, children, elderly,
and persons with disabilities. I mean,
thousands of people are internally displaced
to school shelters that not even fully prepared
or equipped to accommodate these numbers and
provide for their needs. I mean, Israel has
to adhere to the international humanitarian
laws in conflict and its principles. These
principles require Israel to respect the
distinction between competence and civilians,
avoid disproportionate use of force, and have
responsibility for the humanitarian supplies
for the population. And now there is limited
electricity and crossings are fully closed to
let in any supplies. But in ground, all that
is happening are against these principles. And
the international community has to play a
role in ending this bloodshed and killing
of civilians. A resident in Gaza there about
what the last couple of days have been like.
And if you want to keep up to date with
the latest, just go to bbc.com forward slash
news. There is a live page of being updated
as we get more news. Well, we're going to
head to Israel and speak to the country's
special envoy for combating anti-Semitism,
a former member of the Knesset, the Israeli
Parliament, Mikhal Kotlov. Thanks so much
for joining us. How are Israelis feeling
today? You know, I think that what you just
actually framed as how Israelis are feeling
is... it actually encourages me to ask you
the question. Because, you know, when I
hear the framing of what is happening in
Israel, where a genocidal terror organization
holding two million civilians in Gaza
alongside all those civilians in Israel
that were targeted on Saturday morning as
we were in our synagogues on a Sabbath
morning and a holiday in Israel, 5,000
rockets launched at Israeli civilians
from densely populated areas in Gaza,
each rocket a double war crime and a
violation of international humanitarian
law. When I think of the massacre
targeting Jews that indiscriminately
shot 260, at least, young party-goers
on that very day of the holiday, when I
think of the anti-Semitic terror
organization, Hamas, actually designated
as a terror organization, funded and
supported by a genocidal regime in Iran,
holding its own civilians in Iran
in the same way that Gaza, in the
same way that ISIS, in the same way
that 9-11 was a wake-up call to the
West, that genocidal terror cannot be
allowed to dictate the way that
sovereign democratic countries conduct
ourselves. So I would turn the question
to you, if this were happening anywhere
else in the world, not only for
Israel's right to defend its
civilians, but Israel's, indeed,
responsibility to defend its
civilians, where the majority of those
targeted over the last 48 hours are,
indeed, civilians and holding
families of Holocaust survivors being
abducted into the Gaza Strip of
Israel, their entire families being
butchered in their homes, and to hear
the way that the framing that BBC
enables this situation is actually
part and parcel of what enables
genocidal terror to control and to
continue to dictate the discourse.
Well, I think you'll find that
we're talking to as many different
people with as many perspectives on
this as we can. I asked you how
Israelis were feeling, and I got a
sense from you of the anger there is
and the sadness, too. No, there is no
anger. We are fighting for our lives.
There is no anger. Let it be clear.
You said that this is like
Israel's 9-11. Is that because of
the shock that this was able to
happen? It's not just because of
this shock. It's because of the same
modus operandi. This is a terror
organization listed as such in most of
the countries that are listening to us
at the moment. Terror is not a moral
equivalency to a sovereign country
that must defend its citizens from
terror. You cannot speak about both
sides if you actually want to
understand what Israelis are feeling.
There is no both sides. When a
terror organization ravages civilian
areas, enters under the guise of
5,000 rockets targeting those
civilians, breaking barriers, that
there is a fence. There has not been
any occupation of Gaza since 2005.
There has been a blockade, though,
hasn't there, of Gaza? No. No, there
is no blockade because there are
thousands, thousands of workers
entering Gaza every day to work in
Israel. There are thousands of
truckloads. There is electricity and
water still being supplied, although
Hamas has responsibility for the
civilians in Gaza, because that's who
was elected to reign over Gaza. And
there is a responsibility of the
international community and of all
those that cherish life and liberty
to hold Hamas to account for holding
those 2 million civilians in Gaza
hostage to their war crimes, not
only on Israel but on Gaza's
civilians. How do you think the
Israeli military should respond then?
We've seen more than 500 airstrikes
over the weekend. How do you think
the Israeli military should respond?
Well, my job is to ask questions, not
answer them. Well, I'm wondering what
you think any country must do in order
to protect its civilians when they're
being attacked, including as we speak
in their homes, including as we speak.
There is an ongoing war here with
genocidal terror. This is not two
countries fighting each other. A
genocidal terror organization, ISIS,
if you will, 9-11, needs moral
clarity. And this is not just about
Jews around the world who are now
under attack. So to my question, how
do you think the military should
respond? There's been speculation
that there might be a ground invasion
of Gaza, although we're told there are
dozens of Israeli hostages in Gaza
at the moment. Do you think a
ground invasion is the way for the
Israeli government to go?
There are dozens of Israeli
hostages, and many of them are
civilians that were abducted, many
of them raped, many of them paraded
around the streets of Gaza and
celebrated. And the Israeli IDF will
do everything that it needs to do to
protect as it must the citizens of
the state of Israel under attack as
we speak. And every country that
cherishes life and liberty must
protect its citizens from an ongoing
onslaught massacre of its
civilians. And those hostages that
have been held are being held by a
genocidal terror organization. And I
want to make it very clear, alongside
two Israeli deceased soldiers and
two civilians that have been held by
the same genocidal terror organization
in a nine-year standing violation of
international law and human rights.
And each one of those civilians and
every one of our countries must call
for the immediate and unconditional
return, because it is countries
supporting Gaza and enabling Hamas,
a genocidal terror organization, to
hold those civilians hostage as we
speak. And what the IDF will have
to do and the state of Israel will
have to do in its existential war is
not just about the state of Israel.
I want to make it very clear to your
listeners.
Michal Kotler-Wunsch, we've got to
leave it there. Thanks for joining us.
Well, same with this story and
looking at the business side of
things. One industry that's already
filling the impact of this conflict
is the aviation industry, with
dozens of flights already canceled.
Let's get the details with our
business correspondent in Singapore,
Katie Silva. Katie, what are we
seeing?
Well, yeah, as you mentioned, many
airlines canceling flights. The likes,
for example, of American Airlines, Air
France, Lufthansa, Emirates and Ryan
Air all canceled journeys. British
Airways, for its part, told the BBC
that it's only canceled one flight
on Sunday and that it's going to be
adjusting departure times for flights
in the coming days. And that's
unclear if that's because of
disruption at the airport or if
perhaps they want to land at
different times of the day that may
be deemed safer. Many of these
airlines are also offering
passengers to cancel their flights
or to move the dates with no
sort of change fees.
Flights to Israel's second international
airport, Eliat, which is a tourist
destination on the Red Sea, they've
been unaffected. But we've also heard
that Israel's flag carrier, El Al,
it's said that it's going to be
maintaining its flights to Tel Aviv
for now, but again allowing airlines
and passengers to change their
flights. But Katie, this also
comes at the same time as many
Israelis are trying or desperately
trying to leave.
Oh, to leave as well as to get
home. So that's one of the major
issues is that many have found
themselves stranded and with fears
about whether or not the
airspace will be closed.
So one of our reporters, for example,
was actually there amongst them
stranded in Cyprus, at Lanica
International Airport late last night.
Hundreds were packing in, hundreds of
Israelis hoping to get one of the
last flights home. As I say,
there are still rumours about whether or not
the country may close its airspace.
It was hard to get tickets, we understand.
Dozens were waiting to get the seats, for
example, for no shows on the fully
booked flights and getting back into the
country certainly hasn't been easy.
In terms of leaving the country, we've heard, for example,
as well from Athens, the foreign
ministry saying that it's working to repatriate
about 149 Greek tourists
from Israel. Some of them were
due to arrive back late last night
into Greece. But there is
concern about many of the foreign
workers in Israel. I know, for example, Thailand
has about 30,000 workers
in Israel and so governments around
the world looking at how they can get their citizens home
if indeed they want to leave Israel.
Alright, Katie Silva, always a pleasure
to have you on the program, our business
correspondent there in Singapore.
And we are remaining with this
story and we are now going to speak to
our international editor, Jeremy Bowen.
Good morning to you, Jeremy.
Now, you have called this a major
Middle East crisis. Can you elaborate
that for us, please, if you may?
Well, it's
unprecedented that
the Palestinian
armed group, Hamas, has
been able to break out of Gaza,
which is surrounded
by, if you like, a ring of steel,
of fences, wire fences and concrete,
break out
and kill huge
numbers of Israelis,
including many, many civilians.
That kind of thing
is something that Israel hasn't experienced
before and
it's becoming
clear that it's a national
trauma and plenty of people here
compare it to the 9-11
attacks in the United States.
There's even one article
in one of the newspapers here saying that
if you adjust the death toll for population
it's the equivalent of the Americans
losing more than 20,000
on 9-11. So, it's
a big, big event
and the Israeli response,
which is going to be, is already
very heavy military action,
but they think there will be a
land invasion, too, of Gaza.
Now, that also is something
that could have reverberations right
across the region. So,
we're into really unexplored
territory right now.
And, Jeremy, you have been in
the region, you have been in the area.
Just for our listeners' benefit, can you
describe what Gaza Strip looks like
and how that area is to
Israel?
Gaza is
a narrow strip of land
along the Mediterranean
coast, which is surrounded
mostly by Israel,
but with
a narrow border
which also goes into
Egypt.
The Palestinian
population of Gaza is around 2.4
million people,
many of them are descendants of
families who lost their
homes when Israel was created
in 1948,
a time that the Palestinians call the Nakba,
the catastrophe.
And it's an area where people
are mostly very poor,
they live in very difficult and
cramped conditions, they're
mostly not allowed to leave the area.
There are plenty of
adults there who've never left.
And so
it is a situation
which is... life
there is very hard and it's highly nationalistic
and since 2007
it's been controlled by the Palestinian
militant group, Hamas,
which is an Arabic acronym
for the Islamic resistance movement.
And you wrote a
nice read on our website
where you said that, you know, Hamas
blindsided Israel with what you
call the most serious attack in a
generation. And we're hearing stories
of hostages that have been taken
including civilians as well as soldiers.
What sort of challenge does
this pose for the government of Mr.
Netanyahu and the army going forward?
It's the most profound
challenge that any Israel government
has, I think, faced probably
for 50 years since
the 1973 Middle East War.
He is... his political enemies
are already blaming him, saying
that he took his arm off the ball
for a variety of reasons.
It's clear that there's
been, from the Israeli perspective, a huge
intelligence failure.
And they're struggling militarily to assert
themselves. They will succeed in
doing that, I'm pretty certain,
because Israel has got very powerful
armed forces. I think the big
question, which was
and this is
probably an equal challenge
for the Israelis,
is what happens after that?
How do they...
what happens in Gaza
on the day that they leave?
Because the Israelis, who used to
occupy Gaza, and
finally pulled out in 2005,
do not want to get back into a full scale
occupation. But if they send in their troops,
there's going to have to be
some kind of governance
of a territory, which is maybe
small, but as I said,
contains getting on
for two and a half million people.
Jeremy Bowen there,
thank you for coming on the programme. He is our
international editor.
We're going to move away from our top
story. We will return to it later on in the programme
though. Isaac Fanon is here. He's going to give us
some sports headlines. Yeah, took Arsenal 12
goals, but they finally beat Manchester
City in the Premier League. Gabriel
Martinelli scoring the only goal in the 86th
minute as City lost their second game
in the Premier League in a row for the first
time. That's happened in five years.
European football's governing body
UEFA has postponed all matches scheduled
in Israel during the next fortnight
amid increased tensions in the
region. Israel were due to play
Switzerland in a Euro 2024
qualifier in Tel Aviv, but that
game has been rescheduled and UEFA said
it will assess the situation over
the coming days to see whether Israel's
away qualifier in Kosovo
will still take place on the 15th
of October. To athletics news
next, Kenyan Kelvin Kipton
shattered the men's marathon world
record in Chicago. He beat
his compatriot Eli Kipchoge's previous
match by more than 30 seconds.
The 23-year-old finished in a
time of two hours, 35
seconds. And Australia are out
of the Rugby World Cup despite
Fiji losing 24-23 to
Portugal in the final pool stage
match. Fiji got a losing bonus
point and they qualify at Australia's
expense due to their 22-15
victory way back in
September. Isaac, thank you very much
indeed. Now we are
going to turn to
Afghanistan because thousands of people
in the west of the country
are spending a second night in the
open after a strong earthquake on
Saturday reduced entire villages
to rubble. There's been confusion about
the number of dead with Taliban
officials apologising for an early
assessment that more than 2,000
people had died. The United Nations
humanitarian agency says that
more than 1,000 have been
killed and more than 500 are
still missing. I'm now joined
by my colleague from the Afghan
service, Angela Gehr. Good morning
to you, Angela. What is the latest
that you can tell us about this
devastating event?
Good morning.
The news I'm
receiving from Afghanistan
is actually
I can say that is a very,
very, very big...
the darkest
time that we are experiencing
in Afghanistan. The number
that the Taliban
are trying to
share with the media
is very different what we
have receiving
from the people. I think
in that area
we have, we had
more than 20
violets which are
completely destroyed
in the
earthquake.
And also there
is no way for the
actually in the first hour
the Taliban tried to control the medias.
We didn't receive the
actually we thought that everything
is not that
bad what
we
when we
sent the volunteers
group to the area.
Actually
I'm so sorry.
No, don't worry. And so Angela, basically
the Taliban have gone
back to what they said. The numbers have changed.
But what are people saying
on the ground, those who have been affected?
They don't
accept the numbers which
the Taliban is shedding.
Actually, and also
I think more
than 2,000 people are killed.
A thousand people
displaced.
A thousand people are
missing in this
crisis.
And we have
nothing at that moment.
At this moment there are
no big
offer or support from
the Taliban for the people.
Just the
Red Cross and
MSF provided
some help for the people
and the volunteers
group from
other cities.
Thank you so much for coming on to the program, telling us about the
devastating earthquake that has shaken
Afghanistan in the west of the country.
This is Newsday on the BBC World Service
with Rob and Vic.
Do stay with us if you can.
Distribution of the BBC World Service
in the US is made possible by
American Public Media, producer
and distributor of award winning
public radio content, APM,
American Public Media,
with support from Drexel University,
whose model of experiential
education infuses
academics with real experience,
yielding impactful results.
Find out more at Drexel.edu.