Hi, I'm Tiara Vianne. KJZZ's audio service is supported by 1AZ Credit Union.
1AZ offers tools to help build personal savings, including traditional savings accounts and
share certificates. Learn more at 1azcu.com.
This morning, we're hearing at least 700 people are killed on the Israeli side with
more than 400 Palestinians dead in Gaza. We hear from a woman in Gaza.
The last couple of days were harrowing and the airstrikes were very frequent and huge.
Gaza is a very highly dense populated area with each and every missile very impactful
and damaging. In Israel, rescuers say they found 260 bodies
at the site of a music festival, the first site attacked by Hamas.
We'll bring you the story of one family that is looking for their loved ones that has been
taken hostage by the Hamas militants. And in other news, we'll go to Afghanistan
where an earthquake has killed more than 2,000 people.
Rescue efforts are continuing. But first, we're getting a bulletin of world news.
This is Danielle Yawowieczka with the BBC News.
The Israeli military says its fighter jets, helicopters and artillery have struck over
500 targets overnight in the Gaza Strip. Operations are continuing against Palestinian
Hamas militants in several locations inside Israel, two days after they carried out their
devastating mass assault. More than 700 Israelis have been killed.
John Donison is in Jerusalem. The Israeli military says it has
continued to target Hamas infrastructure with airstrikes overnight.
The United Nations says more than 120,000 Gazans have now been displaced,
with many seeking shelter in UN schools. But most believe this is just the beginning.
Israel is massing its forces around Gaza and says it has called up around 100,000 army
reservists. Palestinians are bracing themselves for a possible ground invasion,
with Israel saying its aim is to rescue hostages and remove Hamas from power in Gaza.
Health officials in Gaza say more than 400 Palestinians have been killed so far by
Israeli airstrikes. Over 2,000 people have been injured.
They said power cuts were widespread and were posing a major challenge for medical workers.
Hamas said it had fired a new barrage of missiles into Israel.
Three US air carriers, as well as Air France, Lufthansa and Emirates,
have suspended flights to Tel Aviv. The United States says it's sending
immediate extra munitions to Israel. The Pentagon also announced it was deploying
naval vessels, including an aircraft carrier, to the eastern Mediterranean.
More from Barbara Platasha in Washington.
The UN Security Council has held an emergency closed-door session to discuss the crisis.
The UN Middle East envoy called on countries to exert diplomatic efforts to restore calm.
More from Neda Tawfiq in New York.
Council members did not attempt to reach agreement on a statement.
Not all but many condemned Hamas. The UAE's ambassador to the UN,
told reporters there was real concern that tensions in the region could become inflamed.
Before the meeting, Israel's ambassador to the UN, Gilad Erdan,
showed graphic pictures of Israeli civilians being taken captive by Hamas.
The Palestinian UN ambassador, Riyadh Mansour, told reporters he'd requested an emergency
meeting of Arab League states in Cairo. BBC World News
An independent inquiry in the UK will begin hearings today into allegations that British
special forces killed dozens of unarmed civilians, including children in Afghanistan.
The inquiry was set up by the British government after legal action was brought
by two Afghan families. The US Senate Majority Leader
Chuck Schumer, who's leading a bipartisan delegation to China,
has met the Foreign Minister Wang Yi. Mr Schumer is the latest high-level
American official to visit as Washington seeks to ease tensions with Beijing.
Regional elections in two of Germany's largest and wealthiest states, Bavaria and Hesse,
have dealt a blow to the parties that form the center-left federal government.
Provisional results show losses for the Social Democrats, the Greens,
and the liberal Free Democrats. The Christian Democrats again emerge as the largest party.
The president of Ecuador has extended the state of emergency by 30 days. It's been in place
since the assassination in August of the anti-corruption presidential candidate Fernando
Villavicencio. The extension comes just days after seven Colombians arrested over
the killing were found dead in prison. A hoard of coins believed to have belonged
to a Highland clan chief who was murdered more than 300 years ago has been found in Scotland.
Alexandra McKenzie reports.
The artifacts were also discovered at the site, including a musket and
fouling shot, pottery from across Europe, and a powder measure.
We are starting with the latest development in Israel and Gaza as the numbers of those killed
on both sides goes up by the hour. The Israeli military says that at least 700 people have
died in the attacks overall, with more than 2,000 injured. The rescuers say that they found 260
bodies at the site of a music festival attacked by Hamas militants in the unprecedented assault
on Saturday morning. The wave of attacks launched by the Hamas militant group is being described
as the biggest escalation between the two sides for decades.
In retaliation, Israel launched airstrikes that have killed at least 400 people in the Gaza
Strip, with more than 2,000 wounded, according to the latest update from the Palestinian officials.
Video images show many buildings being blown up in large-scale destruction.
Shops are closed. The streets are empty. The city is said to be like a ghost town.
According to the United Nations, 123,000 Palestinians have now been displaced in Gaza
because of the airstrikes, and many Palestinians say they are now living in fear of their lives.
In the last hour, we got this voice note from a resident in Gaza.
The last couple of days were harrowing, and the airstrikes were very frequent and huge.
Gaza is a very highly dense populated area with very limited geographical
area, like with over 2 million people living in 360-kilometer squares,
which make each and every missile dropped very impactful and damaging.
The offensive launched from Gaza can only be understood in the context of
the Israeli ongoing, decades-long military occupation and settler colonization of Palestinian
land, and the imposition of a system of oppression that meets the legal definition of
apartheid. Meanwhile, Israel also has maintained a brutal blockade on Gaza for 17 years against
Palestinians, refusing its population access to basic supplies and material
needs to survive, and trapping them in amounts to an open-air prison, with restrictions on
right to movement, right to health, and many other associated basic rights.
Yet we were told as civilians to leave. I mean, leave and go where. No crossings are open,
neither the sea. There is also a restriction to some point, if you trespass, you can be shot.
For the last few days, hundreds of Palestinians were killed, including women, children, elderly,
and persons with disabilities. I mean, thousands of people are internally displaced to school
shelters that are not even fully prepared or equipped to accommodate these numbers and provide
for their needs. I mean, Israel has to adhere to the international humanitarian laws in conflict
and its principles. These principles require Israel to respect the distinction between competence and
surveillance, avoid disproportionate use of force, and have responsibility for the humanitarian
supplies for the population. And now there is limited electricity and crossings are fully
closed to let in any supplies. But on the ground, all that is happening are against
these principles. And the international community has to play a role in ending this bloodshed
and killing of civilians. Our resident in Gaza, they are about what the last couple of days
have been like. And if you want to keep up to date with the latest, just go to bbc.com
news. There is our live page being updated as we get more news.
Well, we're going to head to Israel and speak to the country's special envoy for
combating anti-Semitism, a former member of the Knesset, the Israeli parliament,
Mikhail Kotlovich. Thanks so much for joining us. How are Israelis feeling today?
You know, I think that what you just actually framed as how Israelis are feeling is
it actually encourages me to ask you the question because, you know, when I hear the framing of what
is happening in Israel, where a genocidal terror organization holding two million civilians in Gaza
alongside all those civilians in Israel that were targeted on Saturday morning as we were
in our synagogues on a Sabbath morning and a holiday in Israel,
5,000 rockets launched at Israeli civilians from densely populated areas in Gaza,
each rocket a double war crime and a violation of international humanitarian law.
When I think of the massacre targeting Jews that indiscriminately shot 260 at least young
party goers on that very day of the holiday, when I think of the anti-Semitic
terror organization, Hamas, actually designated as a terror organization,
funded and supported by a genocidal regime in Iran, holding its own civilians in Iran
in the same way that Gaza, in the same way that ISIS, in the same way that 9-11
was a wake-up call to the West, that genocidal terror cannot be allowed to dictate the way
that sovereign democratic countries conduct ourselves.
So I would turn the question to you if this were happening anywhere else in the world,
not only for Israel's right to defend its civilians, but Israel's indeed responsibility
to defend its civilians, where the majority of those targeted over the last 48 hours are
indeed civilians in a holding of families of Holocaust survivors being abducted into the Gaza
Strip, of entire families being butchered in their homes, and to hear the way that the framing
that BBC enables this situation is actually part and parcel of what enables genocidal terror
to control and to continue to dictate the discourse.
Well I think you'll find that we're talking to as many different people with as many perspectives
on this as we can. I asked you how Israelis were feeling and I got a sense from you of the
of the the anger there is and the sadness.
No there is no anger, we are fighting for our lives, there is no anger, let it be clear.
You said that this is like Israel's 9-11, is that because of the shock that this was able to happen?
It's not just because of this shock, it's because of the same modus operandi.
This is a terror organization listed as such in most of the countries that are listening to us
at the moment. Terror is not a moral equivalency to a sovereign country that
must defend its citizens from terror. You cannot speak about both sides if you actually
want to understand what Israelis are feeling. There is no both sides when a terror organization
ravages civilian areas, enters under the guise of 5,000 rockets targeting those
civilians, breaking barriers, that there is a fence, there has not been any occupation of Gaza since
2005 and the voices that you are listening to. There has been a blockade though hasn't there of Gaza?
No there is no blockade because there are thousands, thousands of workers entering Gaza every day
to work in Israel. There are thousands of truckloads, there is electricity and water
still being supplied although Hamas has responsibility for the civilians in Gaza
because that's who was elected to reign over Gaza and there is a responsibility of the
international community and of all those that cherish life and liberty to hold Hamas to account
for holding those two million civilians in Gaza hostage to their war crimes not only on Israel
but on Gaza's civilians. How do you think the Israeli military should respond then? We've seen
they're told more than 500 airstrikes over the weekend. How do you think the Israeli military
should, how do you think any other country should respond? Well my job is to ask questions
not answer them. Well I'm wondering what you think any country must do in order to protect
its civilians when they're being attacked including as we speak in their homes including as we
speak. There is an ongoing war here with genocidal terror. This is not two countries
fighting each other. A genocidal terror organization ISIS if you will 9-11 has needs moral
clarity and this is not just about Jews around the world who are now under attack. To my
question and how do you think the military should respond there's been speculation there
might be a ground invasion of Gaza although we're told there are dozens of Israeli hostages in
Gaza at the moment. Do you think a ground invasion is the way for the Israeli government
to go? There are dozens of Israeli hostages and many of them are civilians that were abducted,
many of them raped, many of them paraded around the streets of Gaza and celebrated
and the Israeli IDF will do everything that it needs to do to protect as it must
the citizens of the state of Israel under attack as we speak and every country that
cherishes life and liberty must protect its citizens from an ongoing onslaught massacre of
its civilians and those hostages that have been held are being held by a genocidal terror
organization and I want to make it very clear alongside two Israeli deceased soldiers and two
civilians that have been held by the same genocidal terror organization in a nine-year
standing violation of international law and human rights and each one of those civilians
and every one of our countries must call for the immediate and unconditional return
because it is countries supporting Gaza and enabling Hamas, a genocidal terror organization,
to hold those civilians hostage as we speak and what the IDF will have to do and the state
of Israel will have to do in its existential war is not just about the state of Israel I want
to make it very clear to your listeners. Michaela, we've got to leave it there thanks for joining us.
Well same with this story and looking at the business side of things one industry that's already
feeling the impact of this conflict is the aviation industry with dozens of flights already
cancelled. Let's get the details with our business correspondent in Singapore, Ketty Silva.
Ketty what are we seeing? Well yeah as you mentioned many airlines cancelling flights the
likes for example of American Airlines, Air France, Lufthansa, Emirates and Ryanair all cancel
journeys. British Airways for its part told the BBC that it's only cancelled one flight
on Sunday and it's going to be adjusting departure times for flights in the coming days
and that's unclear if that's because of disruption at the airport or if perhaps they want
to land at different times of the day that may be deemed safer. Many of these airlines are
also offering passengers to to cancel their flights or to move the dates with no sort of change
fees. Flights to Israel's second international airport Iliad which is a tourist destination on
the Red Sea they've been unaffected but we've also heard that Israelis flag carrier El Al
it's said that it's going to be maintaining its flights to Tel Aviv for now but again allowing
airlines and passengers to change their flights. But Ketty this also comes at the same
time as many Israelis are trying or desperately trying to leave. Oh to leave as well as to get
home. So that's one of the major issues is that many have found themselves stranded and with fears
about whether or not the airspace will be closed. So one of our reporters for example
was actually there amongst them stranded in Cyprus, Atlantica International Airport late last night.
Hundreds were packing in hundreds of Israelis hoping to get one of the last flights home.
As I say rumors about whether or not the country may close its airspace. It was hard to get
tickets we understand. Dozens were waiting to get the seats for example for no shows on the fully
booked flights and getting back into the country certainly hasn't been easy. In terms of leaving
the country we've heard for example as well from Athens the foreign ministry is saying that
it's working to repatriate about 149 Greek tourists from Israel. Some of them were due to arrive
back late last night into Greece but there is indeed much concern about many of the the
workers in Israel. I know for example Thailand has about 30,000 workers in Israel and so governments
around the world looking at how they can get their citizens home if indeed they want to leave Israel.
All right Katie, it's always a pleasure to have you on the program our business correspondent
there in Singapore and we are remaining with this story and we are now going to speak to
our international editor Jeremy Bowen. Good morning to you Jeremy. Now you have called this
a major Middle East crisis. Can you elaborate that for us please if you may?
Well it's unprecedented that the Palestinian armed group Hamas has been able to break out of
Gaza which is surrounded by if you like a ring of steel of fences wire fences and concrete
break out and kill huge numbers of Israelis including many many civilians.
That kind of thing is something that Israel hasn't experienced before and it's becoming clear that
it's a national trauma and plenty of people here compare it to the 9-11 attacks in the United
States. There's even one article in one of the newspapers here saying that if you adjust the
death toll for population it's equivalent to the Americans losing more than 20,000
on 9-11. So it's a big big event and the Israeli response which is going to be
is already very heavy military action but they think there'll be a land invasion too of Gaza.
Now that also is something that could have reverberations right across the region so we're
into really unexplored territory right now. And Jeremy you have been in the region you have
been in the area just for our listeners benefit can you describe what Gaza Strip looks like
and how that area is to Israel?
Gaza is a narrow strip of land along the Mediterranean coast which is surrounded mostly
by Israel but with a narrow border which also goes into Egypt. The
the Palestinian population of Gaza is around 2.4 million people. Many of them are descendants of
families who lost their homes when Israel was created in 1948, a time that the Palestinians
call the Nakba, the catastrophe. And it's an area where people are mostly very poor,
they live in very difficult and cramped conditions, they're mostly not allowed to leave the area.
There are plenty of adults there who've never left and so it's some it is a situation which is
life there is very hard and it's highly nationalistic and since 2007 it's been controlled
by the Palestinian militant group Hamas which is an Arabic acronym for the Islamic resistance
movement. And you wrote a nice read on our website where you said that you know Hamas
blindsided Israel with what you called most serious attack in a generation and we're hearing
stories of hostages that have been taken including civilians as well as soldiers.
What sort of challenge does this pose for the government of Mr Netanyahu and the army going
forward? It's the most profound challenge that any Israel government has I think faced
probably for 50 years since the 1973 Middle East war.
He is his political enemies are already blaming him saying that he took his eye off the ball for
a variety of reasons. It's clear that there's been from the Israeli perspective a huge
intelligence failure and they're struggling militarily to assert themselves they will
succeed in doing that. I'm pretty certain because Israel has got very powerful armed forces
I think the big question which was and this is that probably an equal challenge
for the Israelis is what happens after that how do they what happens in Gaza
on the day that they leave because the Israelis who used to occupy Gaza and finally pulled out in
2005 do not want to get back into a full-scale occupation but if they sent in their troops
there's going to have to be some kind of governance of a territory which is maybe
small but as I said contains getting on for two and a half million people.
Jeremy Bowen there thank you for coming on the program he is our international editor.
We're going to move away from our top story we will return to it later on in the program
though and Isaac Fanon is here he's going to give us some sports headlines.
Yeah took Arsenal 12 goes but they finally beat Manchester City in the Premier League.
Gabriel Martinelli scoring the only goal in the 86th minute as City lost
their second game in the Premier League in a row for the first time that's happened in five years.
European football's governing body UEFA has postponed all matches scheduled in Israel during
the next fortnight amid increased tensions in the region. Israel were due to play Switzerland in
a Euro 2024 qualifier in Tel Aviv but that game has been rescheduled and UEFA said it will
assess the situation over the coming days to see whether Israel's away qualifier in Kosovo
will still take place on the 15th of October. To athletics news next Kenyan Kelvin Kipton
shattered the men's marathon world record in Chicago. He beat his compatriot Eli Kipchoge's
previous one by more than 30 seconds and 23 year old finished in a time of 2 hours 35 seconds
and Australia are out of the Rugby World Cup despite Fiji losing 24-23 to Portugal in the
final pool stage match. Fiji got a losing bonus point and they qualify at Australia's expense
due to their 22-15 victory way back in September. Isaac thank you very much indeed.
Now we are going to turn to Afghanistan because thousands of people in the west of the country
are spending a second night in the open after a strong earthquake on Saturday reduced entire
villages to rubble. There's been confusion about the number of dead with Taliban officials
apologizing for an early assessment that more than 2,000 people had died. The United Nations
humanitarian agency says that more than 1,000 have been killed and more than 500 are still
missing. I'm now joined by my colleague from the Afghan service Angela Gehr. Good morning to
Angela. What is the latest that you can tell us about this devastating event?
Good morning. The news I'm receiving from Afghanistan is actually I can say
that is a very very very big the the the darkest time that we are experiencing in
Afghanistan. The number that the Taliban are trying to share with the media is very different
what we we have receiving from the people. I think in that area we have we had
more than 20 violence which are completely destroyed in the earthquake and also
there is no way for the actually in the first half where Taliban tried to control the medias
we didn't receive there actually we thought that everything is not that that bad what
what we we when when we we sent the volunteers group to to the area and and
actually I'm so sorry I'm no don't worry and so Angela basically the the the Taliban have gone
back to what they said the numbers have changed but what are people saying on the ground those
who've been affected they don't accept the numbers which the Taliban is sharing actually
and also I think more than 2 000 people are killed a thousand people displaced
and and thousand people are missed in missing in this crisis and we we have nothing at that
moment at this moment there are no no big big affair or support from from the Taliban for the
people just that just the Red Cross and MSF provided some help for the people and and
the volunteers group from Angela and other cities thank you so much for coming on to the program
telling us about the devastating earthquake that has shaken Afghanistan in the west of the country
this is Newsday on the BBC World Service with Rob and Vic to stay with us if you can
distribution of the BBC World Service in the US is made possible by American Public Media
producer and distributor of award-winning public radio content APM American Public Media with
support from Drexel University whose model of experiential education infuses academics with
real experience yielding impactful results find out more at drexel.edu