This morning, we're hearing at least 700 people are killed on the Israeli side with
more than 400 Palestinians dead in Gaza.
Today, we hear from a woman in Gaza.
In Israel, rescuers say they found 260 bodies at the site of a music festival, the first
site attacked by Hamas.
We'll bring you the story of one family that is looking for their loved ones that
has been taken hostage by the Hamas militants.
And in other news, we'll go to Afghanistan, where an earthquake has killed more than 2,000
people.
Rescue efforts are continuing.
But first, we're getting a bulletin of World News.
This is Danielle Yawowiecki with the BBC News.
Hello.
The Israeli military says its fighter jets, helicopters and artillery have struck over
500 targets overnight in the Gaza Strip.
Operations are continuing against Palestinian Hamas militants in several locations inside
Israel two days after they carried out their devastating mass assault.
More than 700 Israelis have been killed.
John Donison is in Jerusalem.
The Israeli military says it has continued to target Hamas infrastructure with airstrikes
overnight.
The United Nations says more than 120,000 Gazans have now been displaced, with many
seeking shelter in UN schools.
But most believe this is just the beginning.
Israel is massing its forces around Gaza and says it has called up around 100,000
army reservists.
Palestinians are bracing themselves for a possible ground invasion, with Israel saying
its aim is to rescue hostages and remove Hamas from power in Gaza.
Health officials in Gaza say more than 400 Palestinians have been killed so far
by Israeli airstrikes.
Over 2,000 people have been injured.
They said power cuts were widespread and were posing a major challenge for medical
workers.
Hamas said it had fired a new barrage of missiles into Israel.
Three US air carriers, as well as Air France, Lufthansa and Emirates, have suspended
flights to Tel Aviv.
The United States says it's sending immediate extra munitions to Israel.
The Pentagon also announced it was deploying naval vessels, including an aircraft carrier,
to the eastern Mediterranean.
More from Barbara Plattusher in Washington.
The large deployment underscores American concerns that the conflict between Israel
and Hamas could draw in other parts of the region.
They're sending an aircraft carrier with a deck of warplanes, accompanied by cruisers
and destroyers.
Also extra military assistance, such as munitions.
In particular, they want to prevent Lebanon's powerful Hezbollah movement from joining
the fight.
It's backed by Iran, which also funds and arms Hamas.
There are reports that Iran helped organize the unprecedented attack, although the Secretary
of State Antony Blinken said the US hasn't seen evidence to confirm that.
The UN Security Council has held an emergency closed-door session to discuss the crisis.
The UN Middle East envoy called on countries to exert diplomatic efforts to restore
calm.
More from Neda Taufiq in New York.
Council members did not attempt to reach agreement on a statement.
Not all, but many, condemned Hamas.
The UAE's ambassador to the UN, Lanin Acebe, told reporters there was real concern
that tensions in the region could become inflamed.
Before the meeting, Israel's ambassador to the UN, Gilad Erdan, showed graphic pictures
of Israeli civilians being taken captive by Hamas.
The Palestinian UN ambassador, Riyad Mansour, told reporters he'd requested an emergency
meeting of Arab League states in Cairo.
BBC World News.
An independent inquiry in the UK will begin hearings today into allegations that British
special forces killed dozens of unarmed civilians, including children, in Afghanistan.
The inquiry was set up by the British government after legal action was brought by two Afghan
families.
The US Senate Majority Leader Chuck Schumer, who's leading a bipartisan delegation to
China, has met the Foreign Minister Wang Yi.
Mr Schumer is the latest high-level American official to visit, as Washington seeks
to ease tensions with Beijing.
Regional elections in two of Germany's largest and wealthiest states, Bavaria and Hesse,
have dealt a blow to the parties that form the centre-left federal government.
Provisional results show losses for the Social Democrats, the Greens and the Liberal
Free Democrats.
The Christian Democrats again emerge as the largest party.
The president of Ecuador has extended the state of emergency by 30 days.
It's been in place since the assassination in August of the anti-corruption presidential
candidate Fernando Villavicencio.
The extension comes just days after seven Colombians arrested over the killing were
found dead in prison.
A hoard of coins believed to have belonged to a Highland clan chief, who was
murdered more than 300 years ago, has been found in Scotland.
Alexandra McKenzie reports.
The archaeology team from Glasgow University said this was the first major excavation
in Glencoe.
The dig focused on scattered rocks believed to have been the McDonald clan chief's
summer house.
More than 300 years after he died in the Glencoe massacre, an archaeology
student taking part in her first ever dig found the hoard.
The University of Glasgow said the discovery contained 36 silver and bronze coins.
A number of other artifacts were also discovered at the site, including a musket
and fouling shot, pottery from across Europe and a powder major.
BBC News.
Thank you for that bulletin of news.
Hello, your Newsday from the BBC World Service with Victoria Wohonda and Rob Young.
Coming up this half hour, we're going to continue to focus on the conflict
between Israel and Gaza with voices from both sides and we'll get all your
sports and business headlines too.
We are starting with the latest development in Israel and Gaza as the
numbers of those killed on both sides goes up by the hour.
The Israeli military says that at least 700 people have died in the attacks
overall, with more than 2000 injured.
The rescuers say that they found 260 bodies at the site of a music festival
attacked by Hamas militants in the unprecedented assault on Saturday morning.
The wave of attacks launched by the Hamas militant group is being described as
the biggest escalation between the two sides for decades.
In retaliation, Israel launched airstrikes that have killed at least
400 people in the Gaza Strip with more than 2000 wounded, according to
the latest update from the Palestinian officials.
Video images show many buildings being blown up in large scale
destruction, shops are closed, the streets are empty.
The city is said to be like a ghost town.
According to the United Nations, 123,000 Palestinians have now been
displaced in Gaza because of the airstrikes and many Palestinians say
they are now living in fear of their lives.
In the last hour, we got this voice note from a resident in Gaza.
The last couple of days were harrowing and the airstrikes were very frequent
and a huge Gaza is very highly dense populated area with very limited
geographical area like with over two million people living in 360
kilometers square, which make it each and every missile dropped very
impactful and damaging.
The offensive launched from Gaza can only be understood in the context
of the Israeli ongoing decades long military occupation and settler
colonization of Palestinian land and the imposition of a system of
oppression that meets the legal definition of apartheid.
Meanwhile, Israel also has maintained a brutal blockade on Gaza for 17
years against the Palestinians, refusing its population access to
basic supplies and material needs to survive and trapping them in
amounts to an open air prison with restrictions on right to movement,
right to health and many other associated basic rights.
Yet we were told as civilians to leave.
I mean, leave and go where no crossings are open.
Neither the sea that is also have restriction to some point.
If you trespass, you can you can be shot.
For the last few days, hundreds of Palestinians were killed,
including women, children, elderly and persons with disabilities.
I mean, thousands of people are internally displaced to school
that not even fully prepared or accommodate these numbers and
provide for their needs.
I mean, Israel has to adhere to the international humanitarian laws
and conflicts and its principles.
These principles require Israel to respect the distinction between
competence and civilians, avoid disproportionate use of force and
have have responsibility for the humanitarian supplies for the for
the population.
And now there is there is limited electricity and and and
crossings are fully closed to let in any supplies.
But in ground, all that is happening are against these principles.
And the international community has to play a role in ending this
bloodshed and killing of civilians.
Our resident in Gaza, they are about what the last couple of days
have been like.
And if you want to keep up to date with the latest, just go to
BBC.com for a slash news.
There is a live page of being updated as we get more news.
Well, we're going to head to Israel and speak to the
country's special envoy for combating anti-Semitism,
a former member of the Knesset, the Israeli Parliament,
Mikhal Kotler-Vunch.
Thanks so much for joining us.
How is so much for how are Israelis feeling today?
You know, I think that what you just actually framed as how
Israelis are feeling is it actually encourages me to ask
you the question, because, you know, when I hear the framing
of what is happening in Israel, where a genocidal terror
organization holding two million civilians in Gaza
alongside all those civilians in Israel that were targeted on
Saturday morning, as we were in our synagogues on a Sabbath
morning and a holiday in Israel, five thousand rockets
launched at Israeli civilians from densely populated areas
in Gaza, each rocket, a double war crime and a violation
of international humanitarian law.
When I think of the massacre targeting Jews that
indiscriminately shot 260, at least, young party goers
on that very day of the holiday, when I think of the
anti-Semitic terror organization, Hamas, actually
designated as a terror organization, funded and supported
by a genocidal regime in Iran, holding its own
civilians in Iran in the same way that Gaza,
in the same way that ISIS, in the same way that 9-11
was a wake-up call to the West, that genocidal terror
cannot be allowed to dictate the way that sovereign
democratic countries conduct ourselves.
So I would turn the question to you, if this were
happening anywhere else in the world, not only for
Israel's right to defend its civilians, but Israel's
indeed responsibility to defend its civilians, where
the majority of those targeted over the last 48 hours
are indeed civilians in holding families of Holocaust
survivors being abducted into the Gaza Strip,
of entire families being butchered in their homes.
And to hear the way that the framing that BBC
enables this situation is actually part and parcel
of what enables genocidal terror to control and to continue
to dictate the discourse.
Well, I think you'll find that we're talking to
as many different people with as many perspectives
on this as we can.
I asked you how Israelis were feeling, and I got
a sense from you of the anger there is,
and the sadness, too.
No, there is no anger.
We are fighting for our lives.
There is no anger.
Let it be clear.
You said that this is like Israel's 9-11.
Is that because of the shock that this was able to happen?
It's not just because of this shock.
It's because of the same modus operandi.
This is a terror organization listed as such in most
of the countries that are listening to us at the moment.
Terror is not a moral equivalency to a sovereign
country that must defend its citizens from terror.
You cannot speak about both sides if you actually want
to understand what Israelis are feeling.
There is no both sides.
When a terror organization ravages civilian areas,
enters under the guise of 5,000 rockets
targeting those civilians, breaking barriers,
that there is a fence.
There has not been any occupation of Gaza since 2005.
And the voices that you are listening to in Gaza...
There has been a blockade, though,
hasn't there, of Gaza?
No, there is no blockade because there are thousands,
thousands of workers entering Gaza every day
to work in Israel.
There are thousands of truckloads.
There is electricity and water still being supplied,
although Hamas has responsibility
for the civilians in Gaza,
because that's who was elected to reign over Gaza.
And there is a responsibility
of the international community
and of all those that cherish life and liberty
to hold Hamas to account
for holding those 2 million civilians in Gaza
hostage to their war crimes,
not only on Israel, but on Gaza's civilians.
How do you think the Israeli military should respond then?
We've seen, we're told,
more than 500 airstrikes over the weekend.
How do you think the Israeli military should,
how do you think any other country
Well, my job is to ask questions, not answer them.
Well, I'm wondering what you think any country must do
in order to protect its civilians
when they're being attacked,
including as we speak, in their homes,
including as we speak.
There is an ongoing war here with genocidal terror.
This is not two countries fighting each other.
A genocidal terror organization, ISIS, if you will,
9-11, needs moral clarity.
And this is not just about Jews around the world
who are now under attack.
So to my question,
how do you think the military should respond?
There's been speculation there might be a ground invasion
of Gaza, although we're told there are dozens
of Israeli hostages in Gaza at the moment.
Do you think a ground invasion is the way
for the Israeli government to go?
There are dozens of Israeli hostages
and many of them are civilians that were abducted,
many of them raped,
many of them paraded around the streets of Gaza
and celebrated.
And the Israeli IDF will do everything
that it needs to do to protect, as it must,
the citizens of the State of Israel under attack
as we speak.
And every country that cherishes life and liberty
must protect its citizens from an ongoing onslaught,
massacre of its civilians.
And those hostages that have been held
are being held by a genocidal terror organization.
And I wanna make it very clear,
alongside two Israeli deceased soldiers
and two civilians that have been held
by the same genocidal terror organization
in a nine-year standing violation
of international law and human rights.
And each one of those civilians
and every one of our countries
must call for the immediate and unconditional return
because it is countries supporting Gaza
and enabling Hamas, a genocidal terror organization,
to hold those civilians hostage as we speak.
And what IDF will have to do
and the State of Israel will have to do
in its existential war
is not just about the State of Israel.
I wanna make it very clear to your listeners.
Michal Kotler-Vunch, we gotta leave it there.
Thanks for joining us.
Well, same with this story
and looking at the business side of things.
One industry that's already feeling the impact
of this conflict is the aviation industry
with dozens of flights already canceled.
Let's get the details with our business correspondent
in Singapore, Katie Silva.
Katie, what are we seeing?
Well, yeah, as you mentioned,
many airlines canceling flights.
The likes, for example, of American Airlines, Air France,
Lufthansa, Emirates, and Ryanair all cancel journeys.
British Airways, for its part, told the BBC
that it's only canceled one flight on Sunday
and that it's going to be adjusting departure times
for flights in the coming days.
And that's unclear if that's because
of disruption at the airport
or if perhaps they want to land
at different times of the day that may be deemed safer.
Many of these airlines are also offering passengers
to cancel their flights or to move the dates
with no sort of change fees.
Flights to Israel's second international airport,
Eliat, which is a tourist destination on the Red Sea,
they've been unaffected.
But we've also heard that Israeli's flag carrier, El Al,
it's said that it's going to be maintaining its flights
to Tel Aviv for now, but again,
allowing airlines and passengers to change their flights.
But Katie, this also comes at the same time
as many Israelis are trying
or desperately trying to leave.
To leave, well, as well as to get home.
So that's one of the major issues
is that many have found themselves stranded
and with fears about whether or not
the airspace will be closed.
So one of our reporters, for example,
was actually there amongst them,
stranded in Cyprus,
at Lanica International Airport late last night.
Hundreds were packing in,
hundreds of Israelis hoping
to get one of the last flights home.
As I say, rumors about whether or not
the country may close its airspace.
It was hard to get tickets, we understand.
Dozens were waiting to get the seats,
for example, for no shows on the fully booked flights.
And getting back into the country
certainly hasn't been easy.
In terms of leaving the country,
we've heard, for example, as well from Athens,
the foreign ministry saying that it's working
to repatriate about 149 Greek tourists from Israel.
Some of them were due to arrive
back late last night into Greece.
But there is indeed much concern
about many of the foreign workers in Israel.
I know, for example, Thailand has about 30,000 workers
in Israel and so governments around the world
are looking at how they can get their citizens home
if, indeed, they want to leave Israel.
All right, Katie Silva,
always a pleasure to have you on the program,
our business correspondent there in Singapore.
And we are remaining with this story
and we are now going to speak
to our international editor, Jeremy Bowen.
Good morning to you, Jeremy.
Now, you have called this a major Middle East crisis.
Can you elaborate that for us, please, if you may?
Well, it's unprecedented
that the Palestinian armed group Hamas
has been able to break out of Gaza,
which is surrounded by, if you like,
a ring of steel, of fences, wire fences and concrete,
break out and kill huge numbers of Israelis,
including many, many civilians.
That kind of thing is something
that Israel hasn't experienced before
and it's becoming clear that it's a national trauma
and plenty of people here compare it
to the 9-11 attacks in the United States.
There's even one article in one of the newspapers here
saying that if you adjust the death toll for population,
it's equivalent to the Americans
losing more than 20,000 on 9-11.
So it's a big, big event
and the Israeli response, which is going to be,
is already very heavy military action,
but they think there'll be a land invasion, too, of Gaza.
Now, that also is something
that could have reverberations right across the region.
So we're into really unexplored territory right now.
And, Jeremy, you have been in the region,
you have been in the area.
Just for our listeners' benefit,
can you describe what Gaza Strip looks like
and how that area is to Israel?
Gaza is a narrow strip of land along the Mediterranean coast,
which is surrounded mostly by Israel,
but with a narrow border which also goes into Egypt.
The Palestinian population of Gaza
is around 2.4 million people,
many of them are descendants of families
who lost their homes when Israel was created in 1948,
a time that the Palestinians call the Nakba,
the catastrophe.
And it's an area where people are mostly very poor.
They live in very difficult and cramped conditions.
They're mostly not allowed to leave the area.
There are plenty of adults there who've never left.
And so it is a situation
which is life there is very hard
and it's highly nationalistic.
And since 2007, it's been controlled
by the Palestinian militant group, Hamas,
which is an Arabic acronym
for the Islamic resistance movement.
And you wrote a nice read on our website
where you said that Hamas blindsided Israel
with what you call the most serious attack
in a generation.
And we're hearing stories of hostages
that have been taken,
including civilians as well as soldiers.
What sort of challenge does this pose
for the government of Mr. Netanyahu
and the army going forward?
It's the most profound challenge
that any Israel government has, I think,
faced probably for 50 years
since the 1973 Middle East war.
His political enemies are already blaming him,
saying that he took his eye off the ball
for a variety of reasons.
It's clear that there's been,
from the Israeli perspective,
a huge intelligence failure
and they're struggling militarily
to assert themselves.
They will succeed in doing that.
I'm pretty certain
because Israel has got very powerful armed forces.
I think the big question, which was,
and this is probably an equal challenge
for the Israelis, is what happens after that?
How do they, what happens in Gaza
on the day that they leave?
Because the Israelis, who used to occupy Gaza
and finally pulled out in 2005,
do not want to get back into a full-scale occupation.
But if they send in their troops,
there's gonna have to be some kind of governance
of a territory which is maybe small,
but as I said,
contains getting on for two and a half million people.
Jeremy Bowen there,
thank you for coming on the program.
He is our international editor.
We're gonna move away from our top story.
We will return to it later on in the program though.
Isaac Fanon is here.
He's gonna give us some sports headlines.
Yeah, it took Arsenal 12 goals,
but they finally beat Manchester City
in the Premier League.
Gabriel Martinelli scoring the only goal
in the 86th minute as City lost their second game
in the Premier League in a row.
It's the first time that's happened in five years.
European football's governing body, UEFA,
has postponed all matches scheduled in Israel
during the next fortnight,
amid increased tensions in the region.
Israel were due to play Switzerland
in a Euro 2024 qualifier in Tel Aviv,
but that game has been rescheduled
and UEFA said it will assess the situation
over the coming days to see whether
Israel's away qualifier in Kosovo
will still take place on the 15th of October.
To athletics news next,
Kenyan Kelvin Kipton shattered
the men's marathon world record in Chicago.
He beat his compatriot Elliot Kipchoge's
by more than 30 seconds.
The 23-year-old finished in a time of two hours,
35 seconds.
And Australia are out of the Rugby World Cup,
despite Fiji losing 24-23 to Portugal
in the final pool stage match.
Fiji got a losing bonus point
and they qualify at Australia's expense
due to their 22-15 victory way back in September.
Isaac, thank you very much indeed.
Now we are going to turn to Afghanistan
because thousands of people in the west of the country
are spending a second night in the open
after a strong earthquake on Saturday
reduced entire villages to rubble.
There's been confusion about the number of dead
with Taliban officials apologizing
for an early assessment
that more than 2,000 people had died.
The United Nations humanitarian agency
says that more than 1,000 have been killed
and more than 500 are still missing.
I'm now joined by my colleague
from the Afghan service, Angela Gehr.
Good morning to you, Angela.
What is the latest that you can tell us
about this devastating event?
Good morning.
The news I'm receiving from Afghanistan is,
actually I can say that is a very, very, very big,
the darkest time that we are experiencing
in Afghanistan, the number that the Taliban are trying
to share with the media is very different
what we have receiving from the people.
I think in that area we had more than 20 violets
which are completely destroyed in the earthquake.
And also there is no way for the,
actually in the first half of the Taliban
tried to control the medias.
We didn't receive that.
Actually we felt that everything is not that bad
what we sent the volunteers group to the area.
And actually I'm so sorry.
I'm very-
No, don't worry.
And so Angela, basically the Taliban have gone back
to what they said, the numbers have changed
but what are people saying on the ground,
those who've been affected?
They don't accept the numbers
which the Taliban is shedding.
Actually, and also I think more than 2000 people
are killed, 1000 people displaced
and 1000 people are missing in this crisis.
And we have nothing at that moment.
At this moment there are no big offer or support
from the Taliban for the people.
Just the Red Cross and MSF provided some help
for the people and the volunteers group from-
Angela.
In other cities.
Thank you so much for coming onto the program
telling us about the devastating earthquake
that has shaken Afghanistan in the worst of the country.
This is Newsday on the BBC World Service
with Robin Vick.
Do stay with us if you can.
Distribution of the BBC World Service in the US
is made possible by American Public Media,
producer and distributor
of award-winning public radio content.
APM, American Public Media,
with support from Drexel University
whose model of experiential education
infuses academics with real experience,
yielding impactful results.
Find out more at Drexel.edu.